Hello English learners, welcome back to
another show with us here at English Pod.
My name is Marco
and I'm Erica and today
we're bringing you another romantic
lesson but a little bit sad as well.
That's right.
Today unfortunately our
couple is going to be breaking up.
Right, so it's a little bit sad today but
it's going to be good because we're going
to be teaching you
some great words and
phrases that you can use when
you are faced in this situation.
That's right.
And so we're going to
learn some phrases for
breaking up and also some
phrases for staying together.
All right.
So let's listen to the
dialogue for the first
time and see what
happens with our young
couple.
Honey, do you have a second?
Sure.
Are you okay?
You seem a bit worried.
What's on your mind?
We need to talk.
Okay.
I've been thinking and well, I think
we need to start seeing other people.
What?
Why?
I mean, we've had our ups
and downs and we have the
occasional disagreement but
we're happy together, aren't we?
That's just it.
I'm not happy anymore, Tim.
It's not you, it's me.
I know that I can be hard to
deal with and you're a great guy.
You're the type of guy
that anyone would kill for.
So what are you saying you're
breaking up with me because I'm perfect?
Tim, you are too good for me.
You deserve someone
who can make you smile and
make you happy the way
that you made me happy.
I could say that I'll be all
you need but that'd be a lie.
I know I'd only hurt you.
I know I'd only make you cry.
Maybe.
Come on, don't juice me.
Whatever it is we can work it
out, just give me another chance.
I know that we can get through this but
we got to stick together, don't leave me.
I can't, Tim.
I hope, so I hope someday you
can find some way to understand.
I'm only doing this for you.
I don't really want
to go but deep in my
heart, I know this is
the kindest thing to do.
Laura.
Here you're keys, I'll send my sister to
pick up the rest of my things next week.
I'm sorry, Tim.
I wish you all the best and I hope
that one day we can meet again.
I'll always love you.
Goodbye.
Okay, so a pretty sad ending
to this relationship, isn't it?
Yeah, but I don't think the girl was very
moved or very sad by breaking up with him.
I wonder why, maybe she's got
some other boyfriend somewhere else.
Maybe.
Well, as you mentioned,
we listened to some
great phrases and it's time for us to
take a look at them now in Fluency Builder.
Fluency Builder.
Okay, here we're going to focus on
phrases that people use when they break up.
So maybe you've heard these in movies
and we're going to look at the meaning now.
All right, our first phrase as we heard,
she started by saying we need to talk.
We need to talk.
All right, so it's very direct
sentence we need to talk.
So when you tell
someone we need to talk,
you're telling them that you want
to talk about a serious thing, right?
Right, so if somebody
tells you we need to
talk, you know that you're going
to talk about a very serious matter.
Yeah, problem or a breakup or something.
And after that, she told him that
they should start seeing other people.
Start seeing other people.
Okay, I think we need to
start seeing other people.
To see other people.
All right, so this is
very easy to understand.
Yep.
It means to.
It means to create other people.
Okay, so it basically means
that you will break up.
Yep.
It's a indirect way of saying that, right?
Yeah, you're not saying,
hey, let's stop dating.
You're saying, oh,
well, maybe we should
date other people and
kind of giving the idea
that you will still date each other,
but everyone knows you won't.
All right, so let's start
seeing other people.
Now for our third phrase.
She says it's not you.
It's me.
Not you.
It's not you.
It's me.
Now, this is a very cliche
phrase and you hear
it all the time and movies and,
well, some people still use it, right?
Yeah, everyone says this.
I've heard this.
I've said this.
Okay.
It means basically, I'm the
problem, you're not the problem.
I'm the problem.
Right.
So I am breaking up with you
because it's my fault, not your fault.
Yep.
So it's kind of a nice way
to break up with someone,
but actually everyone
knows that that's kind of a lie.
Not true, right?
It is you.
You are the problem.
All right.
So it's not you.
It's me.
And then, well, in
order to emphasize this,
that it's not his fault, she said
that I know I'm hard to deal with.
So hard to deal with.
Okay.
If somebody is hard
to deal with, there may
be difficult to talk to, difficult to
please may be difficult to manage.
Okay.
So it's very difficult
to talk to that person.
Mm hmm.
All right.
Hard to deal with.
It's only for people.
You can use it for a
situation or something else.
No, you can use it for people or
situations or even sometimes things.
So for example, I can say, I find this
problem at work so hard to deal with.
Okay.
Hard to deal with.
Yeah.
So we've seen these four phrases that
we can use to break up with someone.
And well, let's listen
to our dialogue again.
We're going to slow it down a little bit
and then we'll come back and look at some
other phrases to stay
together with someone.
Honey, do you have a second?
Sure.
Are you okay?
You seem a bit worried.
What's on your mind?
We need to talk.
Okay.
I've been thinking and well, I think
we need to start seeing other people.
What?
Why?
I mean, we've had our ups
and downs and we have the
occasional disagreement, but
we're happy together, aren't we?
That's just it.
I'm not happy anymore, Tim.
It's not you.
It's me.
I know that I can be hard to
deal with and you're a great guy.
You're the type of guy
that anyone would kill for.
So what are you saying you're
breaking up with me because I'm perfect?
Tim, you are too good for me.
You deserve someone
who can make you smile and
make you happy the way
that you made me happy.
I could say that I'll be all
you need, but that'd be a lie.
I know I'd only hurt you.
I know I'd only make you cry.
Maybe.
Come on.
Don't do this to me.
Whatever it is we can work it out.
Just give me another chance.
I know that we can get through
this, but we got to stick together.
Don't leave me.
I can't, Tim.
I hope someday you can
find some way to understand.
I'm only doing this for you.
I don't really want
to go, but deep in my
heart, I know this is
the kindest thing to do.
Laura, here are your keys.
I'll send my sister to pick up
the rest of my things next week.
I'm sorry, Tim.
I wish you all the best, and I hope
that one day we can meet again.
I'll always love you.
Goodbye.
[MUSIC]
Okay, so as you said,
we're now going to focus
on the phrases you use to stay
in a relationship with someone.
So let's look at those now
in a fluency builder, part two.
Fluency builder.
So the girl was trying
to break up with him,
and he kept on trying
to convince her to stay.
That's right.
And one of the things he said
was, we've had our ups and downs.
We've had our ups and downs.
Ups and downs.
Well ups and downs are
good times and bad times.
Right.
So the good times would
be the ups and the bad times.
Obviously the downs.
All right.
So it's an informal way of
saying good times bad times.
So they've had their ups and
downs, and he said we can work it out.
We can work it out.
Whatever the problem
is, we can work it out.
So why don't we hear
some examples of how this
phrase is used, and that will
help us understand it a bit better.
Example one, Peter and
Claudia were having some
problems, but they finally worked
out their personal differences.
Example two.
We need to work out a new marketing
plan for this upcoming quarter.
Example three.
After an hour, I finally worked out
the answer to this math problem.
Okay.
So to work something
out means to find a solution
to solve the problem,
to solve the problem.
And again, he kept on insisting and
saying, well, we can get through this.
We can get through this.
Okay.
Get through this.
So to get through something, what
does it mean to get through something?
Well, basically to survive
a difficult situation,
all right, you're lived
through a difficult time.
Okay.
So for them, the difficult time
was this in their relationship.
Yeah.
Or maybe you're having a problem at work,
and you might say, hey, guys, don't worry.
We can get through this.
Just give us one more week.
Okay.
Very good.
And well, as he was
saying that they can get
through this, he mentioned that they
have to stick together to stick together.
We got to stick together.
Stick together.
So again, to stick.
So when something sticks
together, it stays together like glue.
Right.
So they have to be a team and not
separate in order to solve their problem.
Exactly.
It gives you that the idea that they're
going to work together and stay together.
Okay.
Very good.
So let's stick it together.
All right.
And we have four great
phrases to convince
somebody or to say that you want
to stay together in a relationship.
Yeah.
That's right.
So I think it'll help us
to understand these
if we hear them one
more time in the dialogue.
Are you okay?
You seem a bit worried.
What's on your mind?
We need to talk.
Okay.
I've been thinking and well, I think
we need to start seeing other people.
What?
Why?
I mean, we've had our ups
and downs and we have the
occasional disagreement, but
we're happy together, aren't we?
That's just it.
I'm not happy anymore, Tim.
It's not you.
It's me.
I know that I can be hard to
deal with and you're a great guy.
You're the type of guy
that anyone would kill for.
So what do you say you're breaking
up with me because I'm perfect?
Um, you are too good for me.
You deserve someone
who can make you smile and
make you happy the way
that you made me happy.
I could say that I'll be all
you need, but that'd be a lie.
I know I'd only hurt you.
I know.
I'd only make you cry.
Maybe.
Come on.
Don't juice me.
Whatever it is we can work it out.
Just give me another chance.
I know that we can get through
this, but we got to stick together.
Don't leave me.
I can't, Tim.
I hope.
I hope someday you can
find some way to understand.
I'm only doing this for you.
I don't really want
to go, but deep in my
heart, I know this is
the kindest thing to do.
Laura.
Hear your keys.
I'll send my sister to pick up
the rest of my things next week.
I'm sorry, Tim.
I wish you all the best and I hope
that one day we can meet again.
I'll always love you.
Goodbye.
All right, so breaking
up can be a difficult
situation, especially if you're
the one breaking up, right?
Well, I guess it's never
happy if you're the
person who's being broken up with or
you're the person doing the breaking up.
But you know what?
I really noticed that a
lot of the phrases the girl
used to break up were
very cliche, like you said.
They were very common, too
common and kind of a joke almost.
So the phrase, it's not
you, it's me, it's one of them.
And she also said, you deserve better.
You deserve someone better.
Yeah.
That's a very common one saying
like, I'm not good enough for you.
Yeah, but again, it kind of just
it loses its meaning, doesn't it?
And also another phrase
that's very cliche, but it wasn't
in her dialogue was maybe
the timing is just not right.
Yeah.
People say that all the time.
So they say, no, the timing is not right.
It's not the appropriate
time to get beat together.
Yeah.
That's just an excuse for not
wanting to date that special person.
Exactly.
So it can be a difficult situation and
people do it every day through letters.
Yeah.
Sometimes through the phone.
In this case, they were
breaking up in person.
So listeners, why
don't you tell us if you
have any stories of breaking up with
someone or maybe somebody broke up with you?
That's right.
Try and use the language in this lesson
and visit us on our website at EnglishPod.
com and leave us a comment.
All right.
We'll see you guys there.
Until next time.
Thanks for listening and goodbye.
[BLANK_AUDIO]